Mary Louise Foster Papers, 1885-1960
Smith College Archives
Mary Louise Foster Papers
1885-1960
Foster, Mary Louise, 1865-
RG 42 UUID:3fec71d5-9327-4c70-9d29-e133cca685ce
4 boxes (1.7 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of Chemistry, Director of the International Institute for Girls in Spain. Contains biographical material, publications, photographs, scrapbooks, and newspaper clippings.
Mary Louise Foster was born on April 20, 1865 in Melrose, Massachusetts. Between the years of 1878-1883, she attended the Girls' Latin School in Boston, MA, and later went on to study Classics at Smith College from 1888 to 1891. After her graduation, Foster taught Chemistry and Physics at West Roxbury High School until 1896. During this time, she was also enrolled at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in Boston (1893-1895). In 1898, Foster found work teaching Chemistry at Lynn High and Classical School. The next year, she became an assistant researcher in the Lab of Physiology and Chemistry in New York, where she stayed until 1901. In 1903, Foster worked as a research chemist for a professor of Pharmacology at Columbia University, where she stayed on until 1907. While working for the professor, she was also a professor herself in the Chemistry department at the Woman's Medical College of New York (1904-1905). After working at Columbia, Foster was appointed as an instructor at Smith College, where she became an Associate Professor of Biochemistry in 1908. In 1912, she received her Masters' Degree from Smith, and two years later earned her PhD from the University of Chicago. She spent the summer of 1917 at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. In 1918, she became secretary to the faculty at Smith College, a position she held for one year. In 1920, she was offered the position of Director at the International Institute for Girls in Spain, located in Madrid. She stayed there for two years, before returning to Smith as the Chairman of the Committee on Interdepartmental Majors, a position she held until 1927. In 1928, she was appointed a member of the Special Honors Committee. In 1930, Foster returned to Spain to work as the lab organizer at the Institute, in the lab which she helped establish, where she stayed until 1932. It was in that year that she went to Santiago College in Chile to work at the Director of New Laboratories in Chemistry and Physics. In the years that followed, she did a great deal of research, was published numerous times and delivered several lectures in her field. She died June 21, 1960.
This collection includes biographical materials, correspondence, publications, photographs, scrapbooks and newspaper clippings regarding Foster's education and career at Smith College and elsewhere.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Mary Louise Foster Papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Mary Louise Foster Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Search Terms
Foster, Mary Louise, 1865-; Smith College--Faculty.; Instituto internacional (Madrid, Spain); Santiago College (Santiago, Chile); Chemistry--Study and teaching (Higher)--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Women--Education (Higher)--Chile.; Women--Education (Higher)--Spain.; Women--Education (Higher)--United States.; Primer lapidario del rey Alfonso X el Sabio. English.
Additional Information
Related Material
80. Class of 1891 Records
- Awards 1929-1931 (Box 793, Folder 1)
- Biographical Material 1902-1942 (Box 793, Folder 2)
- Certificates and Recommendations 1885-1902 (Box 793, Folder 3)
- Correspondence
  - Anslow, Gladys Amelia 1947-1960 (Box 793, Folder 4)
  - Boston Herald 1898 (Box 793, Folder 5)
  - Browne, Nina Eliza 1924-1928 (Box 793, Folder 6)
  - Chester, Ruth Miriam - 1942-1954 (Box 793, Folder 7)
  - Clapp, Mary Antoinette undated (Box 793, Folder 8)
  - Harvard College Library 1941 (Box 793, Folder 9)
  - Kunz, George Frederick 1929 (Box 793, Folder 10)
  - Library of Congress 1933 (Box 793, Folder 11)
  - Munroe, James H. 1897 (Box 793, Folder 12)
  - Richards, Ellen H. 1911 (Box 793, Folder 13)
  - Sarton, George Alfred Leon 1925-1930 (Box 793, Folder 14)
  - Singer, Charles 1932 (Box 793, Folder 15)
  - Slosson, Edwin Emery 1925 (Box 793, Folder 16)
  - Teagle, Alice Berry 1931 (Box 793, Folder 17)
  - Wilson, Mary Elizabeth 1931 (Box 793, Folder 18)
  - Women's Clubs Federation 1898 (Box 793, Folder 19)
  - General undated (Box 793, Folder 20)
- Degrees 1912-1913 (Box 793, Folder 21)
- Diaries 1907-1922 (Box 793, Folder 22)
- Employment-International Institute for Girls in Spain 1920-1944 (Box 793, Folder 23)
- Employment-International Institute for Girls in Spain-Photographs 1924-1925 (Box 793, Folder 24)
- Employment-Rockefeller Institute 1917 (Box 793, Folder 25)
- Employment-Santiago College 1932-1942 (Box 793, Folder 26)
- Employment-Smith College 1917-1931 (Box 793, Folder 27)
- Leather Research 1941-1942 (Box 793, Folder 28)
- Lectures and Speeches 1898-1937 (Box 793, Folder 29)
- Photographs 1906-1934 (Box 793, Folder 30)
- Societies-Association of Collegiate Alumnae- Boston Branch 1898 (Box 793, Folder 31)
- Societies-Phi Beta Kappa 1915 (Box 793, Folder 32)
- Societies-Saturday Morning Club 1928-1940 (Box 793, Folder 33)
- List of Publications undated (Box 794, Folder 1)
- Alfonsine Lapidary 1930-1932 (Box 794, Folder 2)
- American Chemical Industries in Chile undated (Box 794, Folder 3)
- Articles on Spain 1925-1930 (Box 794, Folder 4)
- Bernard Palissy 1931 (Box 794, Folder 5)
- Bernard Palissy-Manuscript 1945 (Box 794, Folder 6)
- Biochemistry 1911-1920 (Box 794, Folder 7)
- Book of Stones
  - Correspondence 1934-1948 (Box 794, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript undated (Box 794, Folder 9)
  - Typescript undated (Box 794, Folder 10)
- Manuscripts and Notes undated (Box 794, Folder 11)
- Incomplete Publications 1936 (Box 794, Folder 12)
- Chemistry in Spain 1934 (Box 795, Folder 1)
- A Comparative Study of the Metabolism of Pheumococcus 1913 (Box 795, Folder 2)
- Conquistadores 1934 (Box 795, Folder 3)
- Eastern Science in Spain in the 13th Century 1938 (Box 795, Folder 4)
- Education of Spanish Women in Chemistry 1931 (Box 795, Folder 5)
- Guadalupe in Spain undated (Box 795, Folder 6)
- Higher Education for Women in Spain 1931 (Box 795, Folder 7)
- The Influence of Substituent Groups on the Visible and Ultra-Violet Absorption Spectra of Amino Acids and Related Substances 1932 (Box 795, Folder 8)
- Life of Lavoisier 1926 (Box 795, Folder 9)
- Life of Lavoisier- Typescript undated (Box 795, Folder 10)
- Lo que Jesu me significa undated (Box 795, Folder 11)
- A Method for the Quantitative Determination of Indol 1906 (Box 795, Folder 12)
- Modern Education undated (Box 795, Folder 13)
- Note on Formation of Butyric Acid from Inulin by way of Pyruvic Acid undated (Box 795, Folder 14)
- On the Separation of Indol from Skatol and their Quantitative Determination 1906 (Box 795, Folder 15)
- The Pen is Mightier than the Sword 1936 (Box 795, Folder 16)
- Preliminary Study of the Biochemical Activity of Bacillus Lactis Erythrogenes 1913 (Box 795, Folder 17)
- Present Status of Higher Education for Spanish Women 1931 (Box 795, Folder 18)
- Progress of Higher Education for Women in Spain 1931 (Box 795, Folder 19)
- Reviews 1938 (Box 795, Folder 20)
- A Scientific Phenomenon Influential in Human Personality undated (Box 795, Folder 21)
- Significance of a Recent Change in the Curriculum of Smith College 1924 (Box 795, Folder 22)
- Smith Around the World 1912-1926 (Box 795, Folder 23)
- Spain, Still Proud, Joins with America in Studies 1922 (Box 795, Folder 24)
- Spanish Stitches undated (Box 795, Folder 25)
- The Struggle in Spain 1936 (Box 795, Folder 26)
- Studies on the Distribution of Nitrogen in Egg Lecithin undated (Box 795, Folder 27)
- Studies on a Method for the Quantitative Estimation of Certain Groups in Phospholipins 1915 (Box 795, Folder 28)
- A Study of the Decompositions Products of Milk Caused by Lactis Erythogenes 1912 (Box 795, Folder 29)
- Study of Some of the Chemical Characteristics and the Absorption Spectrum of Cystine 1930 (Box 795, Folder 30)
- The Visible and Ultra-Violet Absorption Spectra of Certain Amino Acids 1931 (Box 795, Folder 31)
- Thirteenth Century Book on Stones 1933 (Box 795, Folder 32)
- Three Great Spanish Libraries 1931 (Box 795, Folder 33)
- Triumph of Education in Spain 1931 (Box 795, Folder 34)
- Water as a Basis for the Study of Chemistry 1926 (Box 795, Folder 35)
- Scrapbooks 1941-1947 (Box 796)